Guide to the New York Community Trust Records 1919-2024 MS 3246
New-York Historical Society
- Series 2: Funds, grants, investments (RESTRICTED), 1921-2020
  - Liquidated funds; Trusteed funds; Reports on financial statements (RESTRICTED), 1930-1966; 1968-1972; 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 2.5, Folder 1-11)
    Folder 7: NYCT – Trusteed funds, year ended December 31, 1971
    Folder 8: NYCT – Trusteed funds, year ended December 31, 1972
    Folder 9: NYCT – Report on financial statement, year ended December 31, 1973
    Folder 10: CFI – Donor funds, report on financial statement, year ended December 31, 1973
    Folder 11: NYCT and CFI – Reports on financial statements, year ended December 31, 1974
    Materials in Box 2.5 are restricted for 50 years after the creation date of the document.
  - CFI disbursements (RESTRICTED), 1956-1973 (Offsite-box 2.6, Folder 1-13)
    Folder 1: CFI disbursements, 1956-1971
    Folder 2: CFI Founder and Reserve Funds, year ended December 31, 1967
    Folder 3: CFI Disbursing Fund, year ended December 31, 1968
    Folder 4: CFI Founder and Reserve Funds, year ended December 31, 1968
    Folder 5: CFI Disbursing Fund, year ended December 31, 1969
    Folder 6: CFI Founder and Reserve Funds, year ended December 31,1969
    Folder 7: CFI Disbursing Fund, year ended December 31, 1970
    Folder 8: CFI Founder and Reserve Funds, year ended December 31, 1970
    Folder 9: CFI Disbursing Fund, year ended December 31, 1971
    Folder 10: CFI Founder and Reserve Funds, year ended December 31, 1971
    Folder 11: CFI Disbursing Fund, year ended December 31, 1972
    Folder 12: CFI Founder and Reserve Funds, year ended December 31, 1972
    Folder 13: CFI Disbursing Fund, year ended December 31, 1973
    Materials in Box 2.6 are restricted for 50 years after the creation date of the document.
  - Trustee banks/comparative performance reports (RESTRICTED), 1982-2001 (Offsite-box 2.7, Folder 1-13)
    Folder 1: Trustee banks: performance history, 1982-2000
    Folder 2: Trustee banks: voting power of Trustees' Committee, 2001
    Folder 3: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1982
    Folder 4: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1983
    Folder 5: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1984
    Folder 6: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1985
    Folder 7: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1986
    Folder 8: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1987
    Folder 9: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1988
    Folder 10: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1989
    Folder 11: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1990
    Folder 12: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1991
    Folder 13: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1992
    Materials in Box 2.7 are restricted for 50 years after the creation date of the document.
  - Trustee banks/comparative performance reports (RESTRICTED), 1993-2001 (Offsite-box 2.8, Folder 1-9)
    Folder 1: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1993
    Folder 2: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1994
    Folder 3: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1995
    Folder 4: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1996
    Folder 5: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1997
    Folder 6: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1998
    Folder 7: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 1999
    Folder 8: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 2000
    Folder 9: Trustee banks: comparative performance report, calendar year 2001
    Materials in Box 2.8 are restricted for 50 years after the creation date of the document.
  - Investment reports on trustee banks (RESTRICTED), 2002-2008 (Offsite-box 2.9, Folder 1-7)
    Folder 1: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2002
    Folder 2: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2003
    Folder 3: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2004
    Folder 4: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2005
    Folder 5: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2006
    Folder 6: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2007
    Folder 7: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2008
    Materials in Box 2.9 are restricted for 50 years after the creation date of the document.
  - Investment reports on trustee banks (RESTRICTED), 2009-2016 (Offsite-box 2.10, Folder 1-8)
    Folder 1: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2009
    Folder 2: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2010
    Folder 3: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2011
    Folder 4: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2012
    Folder 5: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2013
    Folder 6: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2014
    Folder 7: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2015
    Folder 8: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2016
    Materials in Box 2.10 are restricted for 50 years after the creation date of the document.
  - Investment reports on trustee banks (RESTRICTED), 2017-2020 (Offsite-box 2.11, Folder 1-4)
    Folder 1: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2017
    Folder 2: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2018
    Folder 3: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2019
    Folder 4: Investment report on trustee banks, calendar year 2020
    Materials in Box 2.11 are restricted for 50 years after the creation date of the document.
- Series 3: Historical materials (PARTIALLY RESTRICTED), 1919-2024
  Series 3 contains legal documents related to the establishment of New York Community Trust (NYCT) and subsequent changes to its governance. Documents related to the founding of Community Funds, Inc. in 1955 are included.
  Materials describing the history of the NYCT include the 50th anniversary booklet (1954) and early issues of the annual reports with speeches and articles explaining and promoting the work of NYCT. These were issued in a series entitled, The Story of the Community Trust (1924-1944).
  Materials relating to the following affiliates are found in this series: Fairfield County Cooperative Foundation, Long Island Community Foundation, Westchester Community Foundation, and The James Foundation.
  The September 11th Fund material comprises four archival boxes. Note: The bulk of The September 11th Fund records reside in the archives at the New York Public Library.
  The Landmarks of New York project originated in 1957 as an initiative of NYCT supported by the Isabel McKenzie Fund. Photographs of the landmarked structures and sites are found in this series. There are also photos of the project founders and commemorative events.
  Materials are arranged chronologically except for the Trustees Committee correspondence (3.2), which is arranged alphabetically by bank/trust company name, and the Donor Biographical Files (3.5) and Distribution Committee Member Files (3.11), which are arranged alphabetically by surname.
  Series 3 is organized into 11 sub-series as follows:
  3.1 NYCT History, 1919-2024
  3.2 Trustees Committee correspondence (trustee banks & trust companies), 1919-2022
  3.3 Annual Reports, 1924-2021
  3.4 Affiliates, 1971-2022 (PARTIALLY RESTRICTED)
  3.4.1 Fairfield County Cooperative Foundation, 1982-1990 (RESTRICTED)
  3.4.2 Long Island Community Foundation, 1977-2022 (PARTIALLY RESTRICTED)
  3.4.3 Westchester Community Foundation, 1971-2022
  3.5 Donor biographical files (A-Z)
  3.6 Oral history interviews, 2019-2022
  3.7 Slutsky files, 1983-2022 (PARTIALLY RESTRICTED)
  3.8 Silberman Fund, 1964-2011 (RESTRICTED)
  3.9 The September 11th Fund, 2001-2006 (PARTIALLY RESTRICTED)
  3.10 Photographs, 1953-2018
  3.11 Distribution Committee member files, 1952-2021
  Some materials in Series 3 are restricted for 50 years after the creation date of the document.
  - Sub-series 1: NYCT history, 1919-2024
    - NYCT history, 1919-1973 (Offsite-box 3.1.1, Folder 1-6)
      Folder 1: Trustee banks and trust companies – Historical file – Adoption of resolution and declaration of trust creating the New York Community Trust, 1919-1973
      Folder 2: Distribution Committee, Westchester Advisory Committee, Warburg Advisory Committee, Mershon Advisory Committee, individuals in trustee banks handling NYCT funds, trustees, former trustees, 1919-1966
      Folder 3: NYCT statistics, 1924-1966
      Folder 4: Community trusts and foundations – Releases, statistics, summaries, 1927-1961
      Folder 5: Resolution and declaration creating the New York Community Trust – Legal opinions, 1933-1959
      Folder 6: New York Community Foundation (proposed affiliate of the NYCT), 1958-1959
    - NYCT history, 1955-1988 (Offsite-box 3.1.2, Folder 1-25)
      Folder 1: Certificate of Incorporation, Community Funds, Inc., 1955-1956
      Folder 2: By-laws of Community Funds, Inc., 1955-1982
      Folder 3: Community Funds, Inc. – Miscellaneous, 1955-1968
      Folder 4: Early programs to teach immigrants English and apply for citizenship administered by NYCT in conjunction with Board of Education, 1959-1965
      Folder 5: History of early transfer of funds to NYCT (extract from September 13, 1961 docket)
      Folder 6: Community Funds, Inc. created "The Common Wealth" for small gifts to be held in savings banks (extract from June 28, 1962 docket)
      Folder 7: Early bail reform projects, 1966, 1972
      Folder 8: Truckload of Trees donation to NYC Parks Department by the James Foundation (via NYCT and Thomas Hoving, Parks Commissioner), November-December 1966
      Folder 9: Creation of disbursing account, May-November 1967
      Folder 10: Resolution regarding acceptability of proposed trust in NYCT, adopted January 29, 1971
      Folder 11: Early workforce development with employer partners, June 1973
      Folder 12: First grant to open Museo Del Barrio beyond school district, June 1973
      Folder 13: Total return using 2% principal invasion, June 1973
      Folder 14: Early focus on child welfare, 1973
      Folder 15: Changes to Resolution and Declaration of Trust (Trust Committee approval), 1975
      Folder 16: IRS rules regarding amendment of the NYCT Resolution and Declaration in 1974, January-February 1976, May 6, 1982
      Folder 17: Resolution regarding custodial account with Chemical Bank for various Wallace Funds, July 29, 1976
      Folder 18: Memoranda – Sidney S. Whelan, Jr., September 20, 1976-June 29, 1977
      Folder 19: Resolution on modification of Resolution and Declaration (paragraph II), March 8, 1977
      Folder 20: Resolution on reasonable return, March 8, 1977
      Folder 21: Resolution rescinding March 1964 Bank Resolution, June 2, 1977
      Folder 22: Resolution and Declaration of Trust – revised and approved, October 24, 1977
      Folder 23: Resolution regarding appointment of one member to the Distribution Committee, November 13, 1980
      Folder 24: Certificate of Incorporation and By-laws of Community Funds, Inc. (as restated to reflect Certificate of Change of Name dated February 3, 1956 and Certificate of Amendment dated May 21, 1981), March 1983
      Folder 25: Changes to Resolution and Declaration of Trust, August 1988
    - NYCT history, 1991-2021 (Offsite-box 3.1.3, Folder 1-13)
      Folder 1: Memorandum to Distribution Committee regarding the priority-setting process, May 29, 1991
      Folder 2: Statement regarding the relationship of New York Community Trust Funds, Inc. Long Island Community Foundation, Westchester Community Foundation, The James Foundation, and the St. James Cemetery Corporation, 1991
      Folder 3: Organizations affiliated with the New York Community Trust, ca. 1991
      Folder 4: Changes to Community Funds, Inc. By-laws, February 1992
      Folder 5: Changes to Resolution and Declaration of Trust, February 1992
      Folder 6: Banking and securities – Authorized signatures, CFI and James Foundation, 1994
      Folder 7: Distribution Committee retreat, June 28, 1995
      Folder 8: Changes to Resolution and Declaration of Trust including trustee approval, 1999
      Folder 9: NYCT Funds, LLC – Certificate of Formation and other documents, 2003-2006
      Folder 10: Resolution and Declaration of Trust creating "The New York Community Trust" (amended June 22, 2009)
      Folder 11: Resolution and Declaration of Trust creating The New York Community Trust (amended April 14, 2021)
      Folder 12: Resolution on replacing trustees, n.d.
      Folder 13: Bound volumes of NYCT annual reports – vol. 1 (1931-1946), vol. 2 (1947-1956), vol. 3 (1957-1966)
    - NYCT history, 1920-2006 (Offsite-box 3.1.4, Folder 1-46)
      Folder 1: Bank promotion booklets promoting New York Community Trust, n.d.
      Folder 2: "Community Trust to Guide Charity," The New York Times, February 28, 1920
      Folder 3: Letter to Frank J. Parsons, Acting Director of NYCT, from Edward Sheldon, President, United States Trust Company of New York (photocopy), March 24, 1920
      Folder 4: Community Trusts, by Frank J. Parsons, address delivered before New York State Bankers Association, Asbury Park, New Jersey, June 18. 1920
      Folder 5: Advertisment for NYCT, The New York Times, September 29, 1920
      Folder 6: The New York Community Trust: Some Questions Answered, August 1, 1921
      Folder 7: The Objectives of a Community Trust: An Inquiry and Some Suggestions, Obsolescence and the Remedy, reprinted from Trust Companies Magazine, September 1922
      Folder 8: Manuscript describing the needs leading to the founding of and functions of the New York Community Trust, December 18, 1923
      Folder 9: Remarks of Hon. Newton D. Baker at luncheon given by the trustees of New York Community Trust, December 18, 1923
      Folder 10: The New York Community Trust (booklet), ca. 1923
      Folder 11: Description of the New York Community Trust, 1924
      Folder 12: Insurance policies and the New York Community Trust, 1924
      Folder 13: Remarks of Ralph Hayes, Director NYCT, broadcast from Station WJZ, January 2, 1924
      Folder 14: Remarks of Ralph Hayes, Director NYCT, broadcast from Station WEAF, 7:50 pm, Saturday, March 15, 1924
      Folder 15: Leadings Lawyers Endorse the Community Trust, November 7, 1924
      Folder 16: Speech/article urging lawyers to consider the NYCT when writing wills for clients, 1925 Folder 17: The Community Trust As Seen by the Medical Profession, 1925
      Folder 18: Report to the Trustees Committee and the Distribution Committee by Ralph Hayes, 1927
      Folder 19: The Rise of the Community Trust, speech by Evans Woolen, President, The Fletcher Savings & Trust Company, Indianapolis, Indiana, April 6, 1927
      Folder 20: In a Hundred Years or So, a talk by Ralph Hayes, Director NYCT, before the Corporate Fiduciaries Association of New Haven, in Woolsey Hall, Yale College, February 17, 1928
      Folder 21: Speech to graduates of Yale University Law School by Ralph Hayes, Director NYCT, May 24, 1928
      Folder 22: Bench and Bar Appraise the Community Trust, (includes excerpts from Frozen Funds, a talk by Ralph Hayes), 1929
      Folder 23: Report to Winthrop W. Aldrich, Chairman of the NYCT Trustees Committee, by Ralph Hayes, Director NYCT, January 26, 1931
      Folder 24: Report to Winthrop W. Aldrich, Chairman of the NYCT Trustees Committee, by Ralph Hayes, Director NYCT, February 15, 1932
      Folder 25: An Appraisal of the New York Community Trust by Members of the Bar, 1950
      Folder 26: Corporate Charitable Giving: Community Trusts As a Solution to Dilemma, by Ralph Hayes (reprinted from Trusts and Estates Magazine), 1952
      Folder 27: They Help the Dead Spend Their Money, by Henry F. and Katharine Pringle (reprinted from The Saturday Evening Post, 1954
      Folder 28: The New York Community Trust: An Administrator of Philanthropic Funds, after 1954
      Folder 29: The Community Trust As Seen by the Bar, 1960
      Folder 30: The Common Wealth, announcement of a new foundation service by Community Funds, Inc. with the participation of designated mutual savings banks as depositaries, 1961
      Folder 31: Footnotes on the Founding of the First Community Trust, address by Ralph Hayes, May 16, 1963, commemorating Frederick H. Goff, and the 50th year of the Cleveland Foundation
      Folder 32: The First Fifteen: The Grantland Rice Memorial Fellowships, ca. 1965
      Folder 33: NYCT-CFI brochure, ca. 1965
      Folder 34: Bookplate used for books as gift from NYCT to libraries, etc. 1966
      Folder 35: Telegraph from Mayor John V. Lindsay, June 14, 1967
      Folder 36: The Art of Giving Money Away, by Herbert West, Director NYCT, Foundation News, vol. IX, no. 5, September 1968
      Folder 37: Coordinate Administration in Giving: Portrait of the New York Community Trust, by Phillips H. Payson, Assistant Director, NYCT and Vice President of CFI, Foundation News, vol. X, no. 6, November-December 1969
      Folder 38: The Story of the New York Community Trust – the First 50 Years, (anniversary booklet), 1974
      Folder 39: Photographs included in the 50th anniversary booklet -- The Story of the New York Community Trust – the First 50 Years, 1974
      Folder 40: Sweet Charity: The Trusts That Prosper by Giving Their Money Away, Daily News, April 5, 1982
      Folder 41:: New York's Own Private Trust Fund, by Suzanne Wilding,: Town and Country, September 1985
      Folder 42:: Report from the Director (speech), by Herbert B. West, ca. 1985
      Folder 43:: Community Foundations Take Off, by Sidney S. Whelan, Jr.,: Trusts & Estates, August 1987
      Folder 44: NYCT staff events, 1989-1997
      Folder 45: NYCT annual holiday party, 1989-1998, n.d.
      Folder 46: NYCT attorneys luncheon, 1989-2006
    - NYCT history, 1990-2024 (Offsite-box 3.1.5, Folder 1-13)
      Folder 1: Miscellaneous events, 1990-1998, n.d.
      Folder 2: NYCT Distribution Committee dinner, 1991-2000
      Folder 3: NYCT donor events, 1992-2020, n.d.
      Folder 4: Case brought against New York Community Trust by Community Service Society of New York, 1995-2001
      Folder 5: Board of Directors Handbook, 2009
      Folder 6: NYCT Annual Fund postcard, 2016-2010
      Folder 7: NYCT stationery cards with photographs by Ari Mintz, 2018
      Folder 8: Archives survey report for NYCT, Janine St. Germain, January 2020
      Folder 9: "The Architecture of Philanthropy" (brochure by Patterson Belknap Webb & Tyler, LLP), 2020
      Folder 10: Speeches by Amy Freitag, President NYCT, 2022-2023
      Folder 11: "A Collection of Our Favorite Holiday Recipes" (NYCT), 2022, n.d.
      Folder 12: "A Taste of Giving: A Collection of Favorite Winter Recipes from the Staff of The New York Community Trust", 2023
      Folder 13: 2024 New York Community Trust Centennial, 2024
    - NYCT history, 1922-1985 (Offsite-box 3.1.6, Folder 1-7)
      Folder 1: Inventory of New York Community Trust records destroyed by fire on October 17, 1984 at Cirker's Warehouse (505 West 55th Street, NY, NY), February 8, 1985
      Folder 2: Materials sent to storage (includes declined appeals, 1970-1973), 1968-1975
      Folder 3: Notebook, 1922-1952 (contains print history, NYCT data, list of Ralph Hayes' speeches and articles, committee members' information, budget information, inventory/supplies, and other data) (Note: FRAGILE)
      Folder 4: Notebook, 1922-1963 (contains NYCT data) (Note: FRAGILE, contains newsprint)
      Folder 5: Notebook, 1923-1965 (contains NYCT data) (Note: FRAGILE, contains newsprint)
      Folder 6: Printers block – New York Community Trust and its corporate affiliate, Community Funds, Inc., Two Park Avenue, New York, New York 10016-9385, n.d.
      Folder 7: Year In Review (extracts from NYCT Distribution Committee/CFI Board dockets), 1970-2021
    - NYCT history, 2005-2006 (Offsite-box 3.1.7, Folder 1-6)
      Folder 1: Application for Confirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations, September 2005-October 2006
      Folder 2: Application for Confirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations (Documents 1-3), 2006
      Folder 3: Application for Confirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations (Documents 4-12), 2006
      Folder 4: Application for Confirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations (Document 13), 2006
      Folder 5: Application for Confirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations (Document 13 continued), 2006
      Folder 6: Application for Confirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations (Document 13 continued), 2006
    - NYCT history, 2006-2012 (Offsite-box 3.1.8, Folder 1-7)
      Folder 1: Application for Confirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations (Documents 14-20), 2006
      Folder 2: Application for Confirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations (Documents 21-33), 2006
      Folder 3: Application for Confirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations (Documents 34-36), 2006
      Folder 4: Application for Confirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations (Documents 37-38), 2006
      Folder 5: Application for Reconfirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations, July 2010-February 2012
      Folder 6: Application for Reconfirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations, 2011
      Folder 7: Application for Reconfirmation of Compliance with National Standards for U.S. Community Foundations, 2011
  - Sub-series 2: Trustees Committee correspondence (Trustee banks and trust companies), 1919-2022
    - Trustees (B-F), 1920-2017 (Offsite-box 3.2.1, Folder 1-12)
      Folder 1: The Bank of New York, 1970-2009
      Folder 2: Bankers Trust Company, 1930-2000
      Folder 3: Barclays Bank of New York, 1976-1992
      Folder 4: Bessemer Trust Company, 1977-2005
      Folder 5: Brown Brothers Harriman Trust Company, 1984-2005
      Folder 6: Chase Manhattan Bank, 1920-2000
      Folder 7: Chemical Bank, 1928-1996
      Folder 8: Citibank (formerly Farmers Loan & Trust Company, First National City Bank, First National City Trust Company), 1929-2008
      Folder 9: Deutsche Bank, 2001-2006
      Folder 10: Fiduciary Trust Company International, 1939-2017
      Folder 11: Fifth Avenue Bank, 1928
      Folder 12: Fleet Investment Services, 1993-2004
    - Trustees (H-W), 1919-2022 (Offsite-box 3.2.2, Folder 1-12)
      Folder 1: HSBC Bank USA, 1982-2007
      Folder 2: Manufacturers Hanover Trust Company, 1920-1990
      Folder 3: Merrill Lynch Trust Company, FSB, 2000-2005
      Folder 4: JP Morgan Chase Bank, 1959-2007
      Folder 5: Neuberger Berman Trust Company, 1995-2010
      Folder 6: Republic National Bank, 1983-1999
      Folder 7: Rockefeller Trust Company, 1985-2005
      Folder 8: J.&W. Seligman Trust Company, 1986-1995
      Folder 9: Stifel Trust Company, 2021-2022
      Folder 10: United States Trust Company, 1919-2006
      Folder 11: BJ Whitehall Bank & Trust Company, 1976-2002
      Folder 12: Winthrop Trust Company, 1997-2003
  - Sub-series 3: Annual reports, 1924-2023
    - Annual reports, 1924-1947 (Offsite-box 3.3.1, Folder 1-29)
      Folder 1: The Story of the Community Trust, issue no. 1 (remarks by Ralph Hayes, February 13, 1924), 1924